ACTWU International Affairs Department Art Gundershiem Publications 5619/032 PUBS
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU International Affairs Department Art Gundershiem Publications
1971-1980
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gundershiem, Art
5619/032 PUBS
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Publications.
ACTWU International Affairs Department with miscellaneous Art Gundershiem Publications
6923056
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
M. Christie, June 10, 2010
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 25, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5619: ACWA Records 5619 AV: ACTWU Audio- Visual Materials 5619 C-S MB: ACTWU President Jack Sheinkman Additional Books, Memorabilia, and Files 5619 F: ACTWU Motion Picture Films 5619 G: ACTWU Graphics 5619 MB: ACTWU Memorabilia Collection 5619 mf: ACWA Records Parts 1-3 on Microfilm 5619 OH: ACWA Oral History Project Records 5619 P: ACTWU Photographs 5619 PUBS: ACTWU Publications 5619/001: ACTWU Collective Bargaining Agreements 5619/002: ACWA Education Department Records 5619/003: ACWA Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks 5619/004: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Files 5619/004 fiche: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Speeches on Microfiche 5619/005: ACWA Bessie Hillman Papers 5619/006: ACTWU Executive Vice-President's Office Files 5619/007: ACTWU Organizing Department Files 5619/008: ACWA Rieve-Pollock Foundation Files 5619/009: ACTWU Operations Department Sidney Hillman Awards Files 5619/010: ACWA Jacob Potofsky files 5619/011: ACTWU Southern Regional Joint Board Files 5619/012: ACTWU Company Files 5619/013: ACTWU Research Department Correspondence Chronological Files 5619/014: ACWA Local 169 Files
Textile industry--New York (State)--New York; Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--New York; Clothing trade--New York (State)--New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Gundersheim, Arthur; Atlee, John S.; Bailey, Martin N.; Balassa, Bela; Blau, Lucie R.; Briscoe, Alden F.; Brown, Muriel Buck Humphrey; Clarkson, C. C.; Feldstein, Martin; Finley, Murray H.; Ginsburg, Helen; Hamermesh, Daniel S.; Hamilton, Edward K.; Hawkins, Augustus F.; Kemper, Peter; Kesselman, Jonathan R.; Kreps, Juanita M. (Juanita Morris), 1921-2010; Marshall, Ray; Moss, Philip; O'Day, Paul T.; Schlozman, Key Lehman; Sharpton, Michael; Sheinkman, Jacob; Sommers, Albert T.; Thurow, Lester C.; Tobin, James; Verba, Sidney; Wipf, Larry J.; Textile Workers Union of America; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. International Affairs Department; American Footwear Industries Association; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; National Knitted Outerwear Association; National Committee for Full Employment (U.S.); U.S. Department of Commerce; UNITE HERE (Organization); Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees
6923056
- Big City Finance: The Next President's Hidden Agenda (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Edward K. Hamilton.
  - Item 1: Big City Finance: The Next President's Hidden Agenda, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    By Edward K. Hamilton. Item is in English.
- Results of Tariff Negotiations of the United States with other Major Developed Countries, Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Product Sector. Standard Industrial Classification (SIC)
  - Item 1: Results of Tariff Negotiations of the United States with other Major Developed Countries, Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    By Product Sector. Standard Industrial Classification (SIC). Item is in English.
- Chart Comparing Senate Finance and House Ways and Means Concepts to be reflected in the MTN Implementing Legislation, 1979; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  C. C. Clarkson. April 18th
  - Item 1: Chart Comparing Senate Finance and House Ways and Means Concepts to be reflected in the MTN Implementing Legislation, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By C. C. Clarkson. April 18, 1979. Item is in English.
- Direct Job Creation, Inflation and Unemployment, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Martin N. Bailey; James Tobin.
  - Item 1: Direct Job Creation, Inflation and Unemployment, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By Martin N. Bailey; James Tobin. Item is in English.
- Displacement and Productivity of Work Relief: Lessons of the Great Depression, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Jonathan R. Kesselman. Additional section 2. Scale and Financing of Expenditures
  - Item 1: Displacement and Productivity of Work Relief: Lessons of the Great Depression, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    By Jonathan R. Kesselman. Additional section 2. Scale and Fincancing of Expenditures. Item is in English.
- The economics of the new unemployment, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Martin Feldstein.
  - Item 1: The economics of the new unemployment, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    By Martin Feldstein. Item is in English.
- The Efficiency of Targeted Job Creation: Conjectures Based on the Early Supported Work Experience, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Peter Kemper; Philip Moss. March 18th. Contains 2 appendix
  - Item 1: The Efficiency of Targeted Job Creation:Conjectures Based on the Early Supported Work Experience, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By Peter Kemper; Philip Moss. March 18, 1977. Contains 2 appendix. Item is in English.
- Employment, Wages and Inflation, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Ray Marshall.
  - Item 1: Employment, Wages and Inflation, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By Ray Marshall. Item is in English.
- Exceptions Nomination and Justification Textile Mill Products and Synthetic Fibers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Murray H. Finley; Jacob Sheinkman.
  - Item 1: Exceptions Nomination and Justification Textile Mill Products and Synthetic Fibers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
    By Murray H. Finley; Jacob Sheinkman. Item is in English.
- Exceptions Nomination and Justification Textile Mill Products and Synthetic Fibers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Murray H. Finley; Jacob Sheinkman. copy 2
  - Item 1: Exceptions Nomination and Justification Textile Mill Products and Synthetic Fibers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    By Murray H. Finley; Jacob Sheinkman. copy 2. Item is in English.
- Exceptions Nomination and Justification Textile Mill Products and Synthetic Fibers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Murray H. Finley; Jacob Sheinkman. copy 3
  - Item 1: Exceptions Nomination and Justification Textile Mill Products and Synthetic Fibers, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By Murray H. Finley; Jacob Sheinkman. copy 3. Item is in English.
- Export Subsidies by Developing Countries: Issues of Policy, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Bela Balassa; Michael Sharpton.
  - Item 1: Export Subsidies by Developing Countries: Issues of Policy, Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
    By Bela Balassa; Michael Sharpton. Item is in English.
- Full Employment Advocate, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  The National Committee for Full Employment. Volume 2. Number 3. October. 3 copies.
  - Item 1: Full Employment Advocate, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
    By The National Committee for Full Employment. v.2:no.3. (1977:Oct.). Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Full Employment Advocate, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
    By The National Committee for Full Employment. v.2:no.3. (1977:Oct.). Copy 2. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Full Employment Advocate, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
    By The National Committee for Full Employment. v.2:no.3. (1977:Oct.). Copy 3. Item is in English.
- Full Employment and Balanced Growth Act of 1976, Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Committee on Labor and Public Welfare. United States Senate. (S. 50 Revised by Proposed Substitute Amendment. Text, Summary, Section-by-Section Analysis, and Background Material)
  - Item 1: Full Employment and Balanced Growth Act of 1976, Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
    By Committee on Labor and Public Welfare. United States Senate. (S. 50 Revised by Proposed Substitute Amendment-- Text, Summary, Section-by-Section Analysis, and Background Material). Item is in English.
- In Step, 1978-1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
  American Footwear Industries Association. August 1978
  - Item 1: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. December 1979. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. February 1980. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. November 1980. Item is in English.
  - Item 4: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. August 1978. Item is in English.
  - Item 5: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. September 1978. Item is in English.
  - Item 6: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. November 1978. Item is in English.
  - Item 7: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. January 1979. Item is in English.
  - Item 8: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. May 1979. Item is in English.
  - Item 9: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. July 1979. Item is in English.
  - Item 10: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. April 1979. Item is in English.
  - Item 11: InStep, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
    By American Footwear Industries Association. October 1979. Item is in English.
- Goals for Full Employment, 1978; Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Muriel Humphrey and Augustus F. Hawkins. February 1978
  - Item 1: Goals for Full Employment, Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
    By Muriel Humphrey; Augustus F. Hawkins. February 1978. Item is in English.
- Major Shippers Report, 1979; Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Paul T. O'Day.
  - Item 1: Major Shippers Report, Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
    By Paul T. O'Day. Item is in English.
- Multilateral Trade Negotiations News, 1977-1978; Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
  U.S. Department of Commerce. no.30 (1977), no.32-34 (1978)
  - Item 1: Multilateral Trade Negotiations News, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
    By U.S. Department of Commerce. no.30 (1977:Oct./Nov.). Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Multilateral Trade Negotiations News, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
    By U.S. Department of Commerce. no.32 (1978:Jan.). Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Multilateral Trade Negotiations News, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
    By U.S. Department of Commerce. no.33 (1978:Feb.). Item is in English.
  - Item 4: Multilateral Trade Negotiations News, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
    By U.S. Department of Commerce. no.34 (1978:Mar.). Item is in English.
- Nominations for Exception from Multilateral Trade Negotiations under Trade Act of 1974: Sweaters, Shirts, Knitted Sweaters, Knitted Shirts, Knitted Headwear, Other knitted outerwear, and swimwear, Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
  National Knitted Outerwear Association.
  - Item 1: Nominations for Exception from Multilateral Trade Negotiations under Trade Act of 1974: Sweaters, Shirts, Knitted Sweaters, Knitted Shirts, Knitted Headwear, Other knitted outerwear, and swimwear, Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
    By National Knitted Outerwear Association. Item is in English.
- Poverty Status of Families Under Alternative Definitions of Income, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  U.S. Congressional Budget Office. Background paper number 17.
  - Item 1: Pverty Status of Families Under Alternative Definitions of Income, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
    By U.S. Congressional Budget Office. Background paper number 17. Item is in English.
- A Reply, Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Lester C. Thurow.
  - Item 1: A Reply, Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
    By Lester C. Thurow. Item is in English.
- Sales Yarn Industry Advisory Report and Tariff Exceptions Nomination for Multilateral Trade Negotiations., 1974; Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Authorized by Trade Act of 1974. October.
  - Item 1: Sales Yarn Industry Advisory Report and Tariff Exceptions Nomination for Multilateral Trade Negotiations., Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Authorized by Trade Act of 1974. October. Item is in English.
- Three Keys to Effective Full Employment Policy, 1975; Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Dr. John S. Atlee. November.
  - Item 1: Three Keys to Effective Full Employment Policy, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By Dr. John S. Atlee. November. Item is in English.
- Subsidized Job Creation in the Private Sector: Problems and Prospects, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Daniel S. Hamermesh. May
  - Item 1: Subsidized Job Creation in the Provate Sector: Problems and Prospects, Publication (Box 1, Folder 24)
    By Daniel S. Hamermesh. May. Item is in English.
- Trade and Employment Effects of Alternative Types of Tariff Formulas, 1977; Publication (Box 1, Folder 25)
  July 27th, 1977. 2 copies.
  - Item 1: Trade and Employment Effects of Alternative Types of Tariff Formulas, Publication (Box 1, Folder 25)
    July 27, 1977. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Trade and Employment Effects of Alternative Types of Tariff Formulas, Publication (Box 1, Folder 25)
    copy 2. July 27, 1977. Item is in English.
- Trade and Employment Effects Under the Swiss Tariff-Cutting Hypothesis, Publication (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Larry J. Wipf. 2 copies.
  - Item 1: Trade and Employment Effects Under the Swiss Tariff-Cutting Hypothesis, Publication (Box 1, Folder 26)
    By Larry J. Wipf. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Trade and Employment Effects Under the Swiss Tariff- Cutting Hypothesis, Publication (Box 1, Folder 26)
    By Larry J. Wipf. copy 2. Item is in English.
- Questions and Answers about Investment Laws in the Republic of China, Publication (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Item 1: Questions and Answers about Investment Laws in the Republic of China, Publication (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Item is in English.
- Unemployment, Class Consciousness, and Radical Politics: What didn't happen in the Thirties, 1975; Publication (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Sidney Verba and Key Lehman Schlozman. August
  - Item 1: Unemployment, Class Consciousness, and Radical Politics: What didn't happen in the Thirties, Publication (Box 1, Folder 28)
    By Sidney Verba; Key Lehman Schlozman. August. Item is in English.
- Unemployment, Sub employment, and Public Policy, 1975; Publication (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Helen Ginsburg.
  - Item 1: Unemployment, Subemployment, and Public Policy, Publication (Box 1, Folder 29)
    By Helen Ginsburg. Item is in English.
- U.S. Government Publications, 1976-1979; Publication (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Item 1: The Unemployment of Nonwhite Americans: The Effects of Alternative Policies, Publication (Box 1, Folder 30)
    By Congessional Budget Office. July 19. Background paper number 11. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Bilateral Development Assistance: Background and Options, Publication (Box 1, Folder 30)
    By Congressional Budget Office. February. Item is in English.
  - Item 3: Sharpening Government's Response to Plant Closings, Publication (Box 1, Folder 30)
    By Ray Marshall; Juanita M. Kreps. November. A Two Year Report on the Commerce-Labor Adjustment Action Committee. Item is in English.
- The WPA: What is to be learned?, 1971; Publication (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Alden F. Briscoe. February.
  - Item 1: The WPA: What is to be learned?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 31)
    By Alden F. Briscoe. February. Item is in English.
- The Widening Cycle: An Examination of the U.S. Experience with Stabalization Policy in the Last Decade, 1975; Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Albert T. Sommers and Lucie R. Blau.
  - Item 1: The Widening Cycle: An Examination of the U.S. Experience with Stabalization Policy in the Last Decade, Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
    By Albert T. Sommers; Lucie R. Blau. Item is in English.
- World Trade Outlook, 1980; Publication (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Business America: The Journal of International Trade. February 11th. Volume 3. Number 3.
  - Item 1: World Trade Outlook, Publication (Box 1, Folder 33)
    By Business America: The Journal of International Trade. v.3:no.3 (1980:Feb. 11). Item is in English.